<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
<?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='no' ?>
<?rfc strict='yes' ?>

<rfc category='std'
     ipr='trust200902'
     docName='draft-ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol-09.txt'>
<front>
<title>WebRTC Data Channel Establishment Protocol</title>

<author initials='R.' surname='Jesup' fullname='Randell Jesup'>
  <organization>Mozilla</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
      <code></code>
      <city></city>
      <country>US</country>
    </postal>
    <email>randell-ietf@jesup.org</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='S.' surname='Loreto' fullname='Salvatore Loreto'>
  <organization>Ericsson</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
      <code>02420</code>
      <city>Jorvas</city>
      <country>FI</country>
    </postal>
    <email>salvatore.loreto@ericsson.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='M.' surname='Tuexen' fullname='Michael Tuexen'>
  <organization abbrev='Muenster Univ. of Appl. Sciences'>
                Muenster University of Applied Sciences</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Stegerwaldstrasse 39</street>
      <code>48565</code>
      <city> Steinfurt</city>
      <country>DE</country>
    </postal>
    <email>tuexen@fh-muenster.de</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date />
<area>RAI</area>

<abstract>
<t>The WebRTC framework specifies protocol support for direct interactive
rich communication using audio, video, and data between two peers' web-browsers.
This document specifies a simple protocol for establishing symmetric
Data Channels between the peers. It uses a two way handshake and allows
sending of user data without waiting for the handshake to complete.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title='Introduction'>
<t>The Data Channel Establishment Protocol (DCEP) is designed to provide, in the
WebRTC Data Channel context <xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'/>,
a simple in-band method to open symmetric Data Channels.
As discussed in <xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'/>, the protocol uses
the Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) <xref target='RFC4960'/>
encapsulated in the Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)
<xref target='RFC4347'/> as described in
<xref target='I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps'/> to benefit
from their already standardized transport and security features.</t>
</section>

<section title='Conventions'>
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.</t>
</section>

<section title='Terminology'>
<t>This document uses the following terms:
<list style='hanging'>
<t hangText='Association:'>
An SCTP association.</t>
<t hangText='Stream:'>
A unidirectional stream of an SCTP association. It is uniquely identified
by an SCTP stream identifier (0-65534).
Note: the SCTP stream identifier 65535 is reserved due to SCTP INIT and
INIT-ACK chunks only allowing a maximum of 65535 Streams to be
negotiated (0-65534).</t>
<t hangText='Stream Identifier:'>
The SCTP stream identifier uniquely identifying a Stream.</t>
<t hangText='Data Channel:'>
Two Streams with the same Stream Identifier, one in each direction,
which are managed together.</t>
</list></t>
</section>

<section title='Protocol Overview'>
<t>The Data Channel Establishment Protocol is a simple, low-overhead way
to establish bidirectional Data Channels over an SCTP association with a
consistent set of properties.</t>
<t>The set of consistent properties includes:
<list style='symbols'>
<t>reliable or unreliable message transmission. In case of unreliable
   transmissions, the same level of unreliability is used.</t>
<t>in-order or out-of-order message delivery.</t>
<t>the priority of the Data Channel.</t>
<t>an optional label for the Data Channel.</t>
<t>an optional protocol for the Data Channel.</t>
<t>the Streams.</t>
</list></t>
<t>This protocol uses a two way handshake to open a Data Channel.
The handshake pairs one incoming and one outgoing Stream, both having the
same Stream Identifier, into a single bidirectional Data Channel.
The side wanting to open a Data Channel selects a Stream Identifier
for which the corresponding incoming and outgoing Streams are unused
and sends a DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message on the outgoing Stream.
The peer responds with a DATA_CHANNEL_ACK message on its corresponding
outgoing Stream. Then the Data Channel is open.
Data Channel Establishment Protocol messages are sent on the same Stream as
the user messages belonging to the Data Channel.
The demultiplexing is based on the SCTP payload protocol identifier (PPID),
since the Data Channel Establishment Protocol uses a specific PPID.</t>
<t>Note: The opening side can send user messages before the DATA_CHANNEL_ACK
is received.</t>
<t>To avoid collisions where both sides try to open a Data Channel with
the same Stream Identifiers, each side MUST use Streams with either even or
odd Stream Identifiers when sending a DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message.
When using SCTP over DTLS <xref target='I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps'/>,
the method used to determine which side uses odd or even is based on the
underlying DTLS connection role:
the side acting as the DTLS client MUST use Streams with even
Stream Identifiers, the side acting as the DTLS server MUST use Streams
with odd Stream Identifiers.</t>
<t>Note: There is no attempt to ensure uniqueness for the label;
if both sides open a Data Channel labeled "x" at the same time, there will be
two Data Channels labeled "x" - one on an even Stream pair, one on an odd pair.</t>
<t>The protocol field is to ease cross-application interoperation ("federation")
by identifying the user data being passed with an IANA-registered string
('WebSocket Subprotocol Name Registry' defined in <xref target='RFC6455'/>),
and may be useful for homogeneous applications which may create more than one
type of Data Channel.
Please note that there is also no attempt to ensure uniqueness for the protocol
field.</t>
</section>

<section title='Message Formats'
         anchor='msg_format'>
<t>Every Data Channel Establishment Protocol message starts with a one byte
field called "Message Type" which indicates the type of the message.
The corresponding values are managed by IANA
(see <xref target='iana_msg_type'/>).</t>

<section title='DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN Message'
         anchor='open_msg_format'>
<t>This message is sent initially on the Stream used for user messages
using the Data Channel.</t>
<figure>
<artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Message Type |  Channel Type |            Priority           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Reliability Parameter                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Label Length          |       Protocol Length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
\                                                               /
|                             Label                             |
/                                                               \
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
\                                                               /
|                            Protocol                           |
/                                                               \
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
<t><list style='hanging'>
<t hangText='Message Type: 1 byte (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
This field holds the IANA defined message type for the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN
message. The value of this field is 0x03 as specified in
<xref target='iana_msg_type'/>.</t>
<t hangText='Channel Type: 1 byte (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
This field specifies the type of the Data Channel to be opened and the
values are managed by IANA (see <xref target='iana_channel_type'/>):
<list style='hanging'>
<t hangText='DATA_CHANNEL_RELIABLE (0x00):'>
The Data Channel provides a reliable in-order bi-directional communication.</t>
<t hangText='DATA_CHANNEL_RELIABLE_UNORDERED (0x80):'>
The Data Channel provides a reliable unordered bi-directional communication.</t>
<t hangText='DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_REXMIT (0x01):'>
The Data Channel provides a partially-reliable in-order bi-directional
communication. User messages will not be retransmitted more times
than specified in the Reliability Parameter.</t>
<t hangText='DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_REXMIT_UNORDERED (0x81):'>
The Data Channel provides a partial reliable unordered bi-directional
communication. User messages will not be retransmitted more times
than specified in the Reliability Parameter.</t>
<t hangText='DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_TIMED (0x02):'>
The Data Channel provides a partial reliable in-order bi-directional
communication. User messages might not be transmitted or
retransmitted after a specified life-time given in milli-seconds in the
Reliability Parameter. This life-time starts when providing the user
message to the protocol stack.</t>
<t hangText='DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_TIMED_UNORDERED (0x82):'>
The Data Channel provides a partial reliable unordered bi-directional
communication. User messages might not be transmitted or
retransmitted after a specified life-time given in milli-seconds in the
Reliability Parameter. This life-time starts when providing the user
message to the protocol stack.</t>
</list></t>
<t hangText='Priority: 2 bytes (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
The priority of the Data Channel as described in
<xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'/>.</t>
<t hangText='Reliability Parameter: 4 bytes (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
For reliable Data Channels this field MUST be set to 0 on the sending side
and MUST be ignored on the receiving side.
If a partial reliable Data Channel with limited number of retransmissions is
used, this field specifies the number of retransmissions. If a partial
reliable Data Channel with limited lifetime is used, this field specifies
the maximum lifetime in milliseconds. The following table summarizes this:</t>
</list></t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align='left'>Channel Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align='center'>Reliability Parameter</ttcol>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_RELIABLE</c>                         <c>Ignored</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_RELIABLE_UNORDERED</c>               <c>Ignored</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_REXMIT</c>          <c>Number of RTX</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_REXMIT_UNORDERED</c><c>Number of RTX</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_TIMED</c>           <c>Lifetime in ms</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_TIMED_UNORDERED</c> <c>Lifetime in ms</c>
</texttable>
<t><list style='hanging'>
<t hangText='Label Length: 2 bytes (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
The length of the label field in bytes.</t>
<t hangText='Protocol Length: 2 bytes (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
The length of the protocol field in bytes.</t>
<t hangText='Label: Variable Length (sequence of characters)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
The name of the Data Channel as a UTF-8 encoded string.
This may be an empty string.</t>
<t hangText='Protocol: Variable Length (sequence of characters)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
If this is an empty string the protocol is unspecified.
If it is a non-empty string, it specifies a protocol registered in the
'WebSocket Subprotocol Name Registry' created in
<xref target='RFC6455'/>. This string is UTF-8 encoded.</t>
</list></t>
</section>

<section title='DATA_CHANNEL_ACK Message'>
<t>This message is sent in response to a DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN_RESPONSE
message on the stream used for user messages using the Data Channel.
Reception of this message tells the opener that the Data Channel setup
handshake is complete.</t>
<figure>
<artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Message Type |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
<t><list style='hanging'>
<t hangText='Message Type: 1 byte (unsigned integer)'>
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
This field holds the IANA defined message type for the DATA_CHANNEL_ACK
message. The value of this field is 0x02 as specified in
<xref target='iana_msg_type'/>.</t>
</list></t>
</section>
</section>

<section title='Procedures'>
<t>All Data Channel Establishment Protocol messages MUST be sent using
ordered delivery and reliable transmission.
They MUST be sent on the same outgoing Stream as the user messages
belonging to the corresponding Data Channel.
Multiplexing and demultiplexing is done by using the SCTP payload protocol
identifier (PPID).
Therefore Data Channel Establishment Protocol message MUST be sent with the
assigned PPID for the Data Channel Establishment Protocol
(see <xref target='iana_ppid'/>).
Other messages MUST NOT be sent using this PPID.</t>
<t>If one side wants to open a Data Channel, it chooses a Stream Identifier
for which the corresponding incoming and outgoing Streams are free.
If the side is the DTLS client, it MUST choose an even Stream Identifier,
if the side is the DTLS server, it MUST choose an odd one.
It fills in the parameters of the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message and sends it on
the chosen Stream.</t>
<t>After the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message has been sent, the sender of the
DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN can start sending messages containing user data without
waiting for the reception of the corresponding DATA_CHANNEL_ACK message.
However, before the DATA_CHANNEL_ACK message or any other message has been
received on a Data Channel, all other messages containing user data and
belonging to this Data Channel MUST be sent ordered, no matter whether the
Data Channel is ordered or not.
After the DATA_CHANNEL_ACK or any other message has been received on the
Data Channel, messages containing user data MUST be send ordered on ordered
Data Channels and MUST be sent unordered on unordered Data Channels.
Therefore receiving a message containing user data on an unused Stream
indicates an error. The corresponding Data Channel MUST be closed as described
in <xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'/>.</t>
<t>If a DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message is received on an unused Stream,
the Stream Identifier corresponds to the role of the peer and
all parameters in the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message are valid,
then a corresponding DATA_CHANNEL_ACK message is sent on the Stream with the
same Stream Identifier as the one the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message was
received on.</t>
<t>If the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message doesn't satisfy the conditions above,
for instance if a DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message is received on an already used
Stream or there are any problems with parameters within the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN
message, the odd/even rule is violated or the DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message itself
is not well-formed, the receiver MUST close the corresponding Data Channel using
the procedure described in <xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'/> and
MUST NOT send a DATA_CHANNEL_ACK message in response to the received message.
Therefore, receiving an SCTP stream reset request for a Stream on which
no DATA_CHANNEL_ACK message has been received indicates to the sender of the
corresponding DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message the failure of the Data Channel
setup procedure. After also successfully resetting the corresponding outgoing
Stream, which concludes the Data Channel closing initiated by the peer,
a new DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN message can be sent on the Stream.</t>
</section>

<section title='Security Considerations'
         anchor='sec-security'>
<t>The DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN messages contains two variable length fields:
the protocol and the label. A receiver must be prepared to receive
DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN messages where these field have the maximum length of
65535 bytes. Error cases like the use of inconsistent lengths fields,
unknown parameter values or violation the odd/even rule must also be handled
by closing the corresponding Data Channel. An end-point must also be prepared
that the peer open the maximum number of Data Channels.</t>
<t>This protocol does not provide privacy, integrity or authentication.
It needs to be used as part of a protocol suite that contains all these things.
Such a protocol suite is specified in
<xref target='I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps'/>.</t>
<t>For general considerations see <xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security'/> and
<xref target='I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch'/>.</t>
</section>

<section title='IANA Considerations'>
<t>[NOTE to RFC-Editor:
<list>
<t>"RFCXXXX" is to be replaced by the RFC number you assign this document.</t>
</list>
]</t>
<t>IANA is asked to update the reference of an already existing SCTP PPID
assignment (<xref target='iana_ppid'/>) and to create a new standalone registry
with its own URL for the DCEP (<xref target='iana_dcep_registry'/>) containing
two new registration tables (<xref target='iana_msg_type'/> and
<xref target='iana_channel_type'/>).</t>

<section title='SCTP Payload Protocol Identifier'
         anchor='iana_ppid'>
<t>This document uses one already registered SCTP Payload Protocol
Identifier (PPID) named "WebRTC Control".
<xref target='RFC4960'/> creates the registry
"SCTP Payload Protocol Identifiers" from which this identifier was assigned.
IANA is requested to update the reference of this assignment to point to this
document and to update the name. The corresponding date should be kept.</t>
<t>Therefore this assignment should be updated to read:</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align='left'>Value</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>SCTP PPID</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>Reference</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>Date</ttcol>
<c>WebRTC DCEP</c> <c>50</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c> <c>2013-09-20</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section title='New Standalone Registry for the DCEP'
         anchor='iana_dcep_registry'>
<t>IANA is requested to create a new standalone registry (aka a webpage) with
its own URL for the Data Channel Establishment Protocol (DCEP).
The title should be "Data Channel Establishment Protocol (DCEP) Parameters".
It will contain the two tables as described in <xref target='iana_msg_type'/>
and <xref target='iana_channel_type'/>.</t>

<section title='New Message Type Registry'
         anchor ='iana_msg_type'>
<t>IANA is requested to create a new registration table "Message Type Registry"
for the Data Channel Establishment Protocol (DCEP) to manage the one byte
"Message Type" field in DCEP messages (see <xref target='msg_format'/>).
This registration table should be part of the registry described in
<xref target='iana_dcep_registry'/>.</t>
<t>The assignment of new message types is done through an RFC required action,
as defined in <xref target='RFC5226'/>.
Documentation of the new message type MUST contain the following information:
<list style="numbers">
<t>A name for the new message type;</t>
<t>A detailed procedural description of the use of messages with the new type
within the operation of the Data Channel Establishment Protocol.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Initially the following values need to be registered:</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align='left'>Name</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>Reference</ttcol>
<c>Reserved</c>          <c>0x00     </c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>Reserved</c>          <c>0x01     </c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_ACK</c>  <c>0x02     </c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN</c> <c>0x03     </c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>Unassigned</c>        <c>0x04-0xfe</c> <c>         </c>
<c>Reserved</c>          <c>0xff     </c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
</texttable>
<t>Please note that the values 0x00 and 0x01 are reserved to avoid
interoperability problems, since they have been used in earlier versions
of the document.
The value 0xff has been reserved for future extensibility.
The range of possible values is from 0x00 to 0xff.</t>
</section>

<section title='New Channel Type Registry'
         anchor='iana_channel_type'>
<t>IANA is requested to create a new registration table "Channel Type Registry"
for the Data Channel Establishment Protocol to manage the one byte
"Channel Type" field in DATA_CHANNEL_OPEN messages
(see <xref target='open_msg_format'/>).
This registration table should be part of the registry described in
<xref target='iana_dcep_registry'/>.</t>
<t>The assignment of new message types is done through an RFC required action,
as defined in <xref target='RFC5226'/>.
Documentation of the new Channel Type MUST contain the following information:
<list style="numbers">
<t>A name for the new Channel Type;</t>
<t>A detailed procedural description of the user message handling for
Data Channels using this new Channel Type.</t>
</list>
Please note that if new Channel Types support ordered and unordered message
delivery, the high order bit SHOULD be used to indicate whether the message
delivery is unordered or not.</t>
<t>Initially the following values need to be registered:</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align='left'>Name</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align='left'>Reference</ttcol>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_RELIABLE</c>                          <c>0x00</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_RELIABLE_UNORDERED</c>                <c>0x80</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_REXMIT</c>           <c>0x01</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_REXMIT_UNORDERED</c> <c>0x81</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_TIMED</c>            <c>0x02</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>DATA_CHANNEL_PARTIAL_RELIABLE_TIMED_UNORDERED</c>  <c>0x82</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>Reserved</c>                                       <c>0x7f</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>Reserved</c>                                       <c>0xff</c> <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
<c>Unassigned</c>                                     <c>rest</c> <c>         </c>
</texttable>
<t>Please note that the values 0x7f and 0xff have been reserved for future
extensibility.
The range of possible values is from 0x00 to 0xff.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section title='Acknowledgments'>
<t>The authors wish to thank
Harald Alvestrand,
Richard Barnes,
Adam Bergkvist,
Barry Dingle,
Stefan Håkansson,
Cullen Jennings,
Paul Kyzivat,
Doug Leonard,
Irene Ruengeler,
Randall Stewart,
Peter Thatcher,
Martin Thompson,
Justin Uberti,
and many others for their invaluable comments.</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
<references title='Normative References'>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4347'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4960'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5226'?>
<?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps'?>
<?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel' ?>
</references>

<references title='Informational References'>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.6455'?>
<?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security'?>
<?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch'?>
</references>
</back>

</rfc>
